Finding Aid for George S. May Papers 1946-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George S. May Papers 1946-1999 1987-1995
May, George S.
Eastern Michigan University professor of history; University of Michigan student notebooks, research materials on the history of the automobile in Michigan.
88547 Aa 2
2.2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection was donated by George May in March, 1999 (donor # 2920 ).
The collection is open for research.
George S. May graduated from the University of Michigan, receiving all of his degrees in history. Between 1956 and 1966 he was employed by the Michigan Historical Commission, heading up the state's historical marker program, and serving for one year as editor of Michigan History Magazine. Subsequently, May became a professor of history at Eastern Michigan University. Throughout his career, May has written extensively on topics relating to Michigan history. Included are a biographical study of R. E. Olds and a history of the automobile industry in Michigan entitled, A Most Unique Machine.
In 1987 May was commissioned by the Henry Ford Museum to write a book on the affect of the automobile on life in America. The proposed volume would cover the history of the automobile from the creation of the first horseless carriage up to the present. It was to be titled "The Automobile in American Life" and was intended to be part of a Henry Ford exhibition of the same name in 1990-1991.
As part of his research, May interviewed people with different perspectives on the automobile industry, including factory workers, car salesmen, industry executives, patent lawyers, and those who experienced the change from a horse and carriage lifestyle to an automotive one. These interviews included discussion on the ways the automobile helped shape a new culture and literally changed the landscape in America. The proposed "The Automobile in American Life" volume was never published.
The George May papers consists primarily of research files from his study of the history of the automobile. There is also a small series of student notebooks compiled while he was a student of history at the University of Michigan. The series in the collection are Automobile History Research and University of Michigan Student Notebooks.
Subjects:
Dumond, Dwight Lowell, 1895-1976; Eldersveld, Samuel James.; Fine, Sidney, 1920-; May, George S.; University of Michigan. Dept. of History.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Political Science.; University of Michigan--Student notebooks.; Automobile industry and trade.; Oral history.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Shettler, Reuben.; Smith, Frederick.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Automobile History Research
  The Automobile History Research series includes biographical materials on several early automobile manufacturers, interview transcripts, audio tapes of interviews, the manuscript for his automobile history, and correspondence with the Henry Ford Museum about the project. The interviews were conducted in 1978-1979, and contain a wide variance of perspectives on how the automobile changed American life and the new businesses it spawned. The audio tapes contain interviews May conducted for his research. These tapes are indexed. This series also contains the complete text of The Automobile in American Life, both the original text, and the shorter, edited version intended for publication by the Henry Ford Museum. Included here are notes and newsclippings used for research in each individual chapter as well as intended illustrations. The correspondence file consists of exchanges with the Henry Ford Museum and the editor of Michigan History about attempts to get The Automobile in American Life published after the Henry Ford Museum did not use it for its exhibition.
  - Biographical Research Materials
    - Oliver Barthell (Box 1)
    - Donald Dolson (Box 1)
    - R.E. Olds (Box 1)
    - Benjamin Briscoe (Box 1)
    - Frank Briscoe 1954 (Box 1)
    - Alanson Brush (Box 1)
    - Charles B. King (Box 1)
  - Interview Transcripts
    - Rosalind Arbour 1978 (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Harry B. Atkins 1979 (Box 1)
    - Milton Barnes 1979 (Box 1)
      includes biographical material
    - C. Eugene Beatly (incomplete) (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Dorothy Bird 1979 (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Lee Bunton 1979 (Box 1)
    - John Burton 1979 (Box 1)
    - Edward S. Chipman 1979 (Box 1)
    - C. Townsend Clark 1979 (Box 1)
    - Oscar Collins 1979 (Box 1)
    - Virginia Cooper 1978 (Box 1)
    - Donald Disbrow 1978 (Box 1)
    - Herbert Estes 1979 (Box 1)
    - Raymond Fischer 1978 (Box 1)
    - Foster Fletcher 1979 (Box 1)
    - James E. Green 1979 (Box 1)
    - Sydney and Barbara Guy 1978 (Box 1)
    - Thurlow L. Hansen 1979 (Box 1)
    - Ellen Hood 1978 (Box 1)
    - Arthur Howard 1978 (Box 1)
    - L. Gaylord Hubbard 1974-1975, 2 folders (Box 1)
      (correspondence and biographical materials)
    - John Livingston, circa 1978-1979 (Box 1)
    - A. P. Marshall 1979 (Box 1)
    - Tish May 1979 (Box 1)
    - Mr. and Mrs. J.F. Meulman 1979 (Box 1)
    - Harold Ormond 1978 (Box 1)
    - George Palmer 1979 (Box 1)
    - Frank Pitt 1978 (Box 1)
      includes some biographical information
    - Vernon Satterwaite 1979 (Box 1)
    - John Simpson 1979 (Box 1)
    - Byron Spence 1979 (Box 1)
    - Jean Sundquist 1978 (Box 1)
    - Paul Szonyi, circa 1978-1979 (Box 1)
    - Karl Tunnicliffe 1978 (Box 1)
    - Dorsey Walker 1979 (Box 1)
    - James Westfall 1978 (Box 1)
  - Audio Tapes of interviews
    - Index of tapes 1999 (Box 1)
    - Cassette tapes containing interviews with individuals about the history of the automobile 1978-1979, 2 boxes (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of automobile history and related
    - The Automobile in American Life Manuscript 1987-1990
      - Chapters 1-7, 7 folders (Box 2)
      - Manuscript Sources (Box 2)
    - Edited for Publication copy of The Automobile in American Life Chapters 1-7, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Notes and Newsclippings used for Manuscripts, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Notes and Newsclipping used for The Automobile in American Life Chapters 2-7, 6 folders (Box 2)
    - Illustrations for books (Box 2)
    - Photographs (Box 2)
    - Henry Ford Museum's Exhibitions Reviews (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with Henry Ford Museum 1990-1995 (Box 2)
- University of Michigan Student Notebooks
  May's University of Michigan Student Notebooks have his extensive class notes and syllabi from his coursework. The classes were political science and American history classes taught by Sidney Fine, Samuel Eldersveld, and Dwight Dumond.
  - Notes taken from classes at the U-M 1946-1947, 1950-1951, 2 volumes (Box 3)